A Guide to the Mountain Lake Biological Station Files, 1930-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Mountain Lake Biological Station Files 1930-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-6/9/3.082
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
There are no restrictions
Acquisition Information
The papers were an archival transfer from the Mountain Lake Biological Station through Eric Nagy, 2008 November 7.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Mountain Lake Biological Station is a field research and teaching facility located in the deciduous hardwood forest of the Appalachian Mountains of southwestern Virginia. It is the field station of the Biology Department at the University of Virginia. It has two modern laboratories and full living accommodations available on site.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of archival and educational items from the Mountain Lake Biological Station, University of Virginia, ca. 1930-1989, and undated, ca. 1,525 items (7 boxes, ca. 3.5 linear feet). The collection includes watercolors and drawings of native plants, chiefly by Cristina Chace Capehart, Susan Carlton Smith and Lucille Walton; photographs, slides, illustration cuts and printing blocks, and specifications for a research and teaching laboratory, 1939.
Of special interest in the collection are two prints from the double folio editions of Audubon's "Birds of America" and "Viviparous quadrupeds of North America" and twelve from the royal octavo editions.
The collection also includes two 8mm film reels of a groundbreaking ceremony for a science lab (color, no sound, on 4-inch reels).
Photographs include scenery, buildings, classes, groups and individuals. Among the latter are Augustin Grattinger, John Bowie Laing, Ivey Foreman Lewis, Charles Theodore Mohr, Lewis David Schweinitz, and Frederick Leonard Schoew.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series, Series I: Papers and Artwork of the Mountain Lake Biological Station and Series II: Audubon Prints. The watercolors and ink drawings of plants are in alphabetical order according to their scientific name according to the respective artist.
Contents List
- Series I: Papers and Artwork of the Mountain Lake Biological Station
  - 1953 July 11 Award of the "Degree of Nomenclator cum Laude" to Lucile Burns for proposing the name Stonehenge for the new picnic grounds, (oversize)
  - 1946, n.d. Cristina Chace Capehart - Watercolors - Plants (Box-folder 1:1)
  - n.d. Cristina Chace Capehart - Large Drawings and Watercolors of Highly Edible and Poisonous Mushrooms, (oversize)
  - n.d. Civil War Rifles - photographs and information about artifacts excavated at Mountain Lake, including bullets, a gun barrel, and bayonet dug up during excavations for Clayton Hall. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 1989, n.d. Copied Photographs, Documents and Maps for research about the buildings and people at Mountain Lake, including original photographs of the home of Augustin Gattinger (Box-folder 1:3)
  - n.d. Groundbreaking ceremony for a science lab; two 8mm film reels color, no sound, on 4-inch reels (Film reels 0306; 0307)
  - 1940 August 5 Life Article "Mountain Lake in Virginia's Alleghenies is Summer Paradise for Naturalists", (oversize)
  - 1956, 1961 Mountain Lake Echoes Covers, Lithographic Negative, (oversize)
  - 1962 Mountain Lake Echoes Cover, Lithographic Negative, (oversize)
  - n.d. Music and Words to "The Arrival of a Tub," and illustrated by a pen-and-ink drawing, (oversize)
  - n.d. Negatives (Box-folder 1:4)
  - n.d. Photograph - Lewis David Schweinitz (Box-folder 1:5)
  - 1977, n.d. Photographs - Buildings at Mountain Lake Biological Station, including photographs of damage to various rooms (Box-folder 1:6)
  - n.d. Photographs - Classes, Groups, and Individuals, including Dr. Ivey Foreman Lewis (Box-folder 1:7)
  - n.d. Photographs - Landscapes and Scenery, including Mountain Lake, Hoge's Pond, Farrier's Pond, McClarity's Pond, Kessinger's Pond, V.P.I's Pond I and II (Virginia Polytechnical Institute), Evan's Pond, Big Stony Creek, and the Cascades (Box-folder 1:8)
  - 1934-1981, n.d. Photographs - Snapshots of buildings, staff, faculty, students, and scenery (Box-folder 1:9)
  - n.d. Photographs of Augustin Gattinger (1825-1903); John Bowie Laing (1876-1945); Charles Theodore Mohr (1824-1901); Frederick Leonard Schoew (1866-1939); and a Military Funeral, possibly from the [Spanish American War?], (oversize)
  - n.d. Ten Photographs of the Road, Mountain Scenes, [Summer ?] Cottage, and Lake at Mountain Lake Biological Station, (oversize)
  - 1984-1991, n.d. Photographs removed from Album, chiefly people and activities at the Mountain Lake Biological Station (Box-folder 2:1)
  - 1960-1965, n.d. Photographs removed from Scrapbook, chiefly people and activities at the Mountain Lake Biological Station (Box-folder 2:2)
  - 1957-1960 Poster Contest Ideas for a Mountain Lake Flag when Dr. Hobbs was Director (Oversize T-39)
  - 1930-1939 Scrapbook of news clippings and photographs of the Mountain Lake Biological Station, focusing on social and scientific activities, staff, faculty, students, and classes (Box-folder 2:3)
  - 1940-1951, 1958 Scrapbook of photographs of the Mountain Lake Biological Station, focusing on social and scientific activities, staff, faculty, students, and classes, and two certificates of good behavior and merit (Box-folder 2:4)
  - 1938 Scrapbook of photographs of the Mountain Lake Biological Station, focusing on staff, faculty, students, and geological features of the area, with a note from Ivey Foreman Lewis to Dr. Reynolds, saying it was presented by Joe Roberts in 1938 (Oversize T-39)
  - 1938, 1952-1960 Scrapbook of news clippings and photographs of the Mountain Lake Biological Station, focusing on social and scientific activities, staff, faculty, students, and classes (Oversize T-39)
  - [1927?], 1934-1938 Scrapbook Pages - Unbound, with news clipping about Christopher Gist's visit in 1751, hand-drawn map of Mountain Lake and surrounding area, and photographs of students, staff, faculty, and scenery (Box-folder 2:5)
  - ca. 1941-1960 Scrapbook Pages - Unbound, including one page of sketches of animals, insects, etc. and identified photographs of social and scientific activities, individuals, and classes of various terms (Oversize T-39)
  - 1956, 1969-1983 Slides, including rattlesnake, red and blue crawdads, red salamander, and bird nesting sites, mostly from the Mountain Lake Biological Station area (Box-folder 3:1)
  - n.d. Slides, Students and their projects in the various sciences (Box-folder 3:2)
  - n.d. Slides - Africa scenes and Educational (Box-folder 3:3)
  - ca. 1930-1981, n.d. Slides - Students, classes, staff, and faculty of the Mountain Lake Biological Station (Box-folder 3:4)
  - ca. 1952-1989, n.d. Slides, including scenery, topography, and geology of the area surrounding Mountain Lake and the New River (Box-folder 3:5)
  - 1947-1949, n.d. Susan Carlton Smith - Large Drawings and Watercolors of Plants, including Russula emetica mushroom, Fire Pink, Indian Pipe, Mountain Laurel, and Flame Azalea, (oversize)
  - [1939]"Specifications for Research Teaching Laboratory Mountain Lake Biological Station, Mountain Lake, Virginia" (Box-folder 4:1)
  - [1939]"Specifications for Research Teaching Laboratory Mountain Lake Biological Station, Mountain Lake, Virginia" Copy 2 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - [1939] "Specifications for Research Teaching Laboratory Mountain Lake Biological Station, Mountain Lake, Virginia" Copy 3 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - 1971 - 1976 Lucille Walton: Ink Line Drawings, Plants (Box-folder 4:4)
  - 1977 - 1978 Lucille Walton: Ink Line Drawings, Landscapes (Box-folder 4:5)
  - n.d. Lucille Walton: Water Colors, Plants (Box-folder 4:6)
  - n.d. Large Watercolor of a Cell by Lucille Walton, (oversize)
  - n.d.[Steel?] Illustration Cuts (Box 5)
  - n.d. [Steel?] Illustration Cuts (Box 6)
  - n.d.[Steel?] Illustration Cuts (Box 7)
- Series II: Audubon Prints
  - 1845"American Bison or Buffalo" printed by J.T. Bowen, Philadelphia, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - 1843"American Cross Fox" printed by J.T. Bowen, Philadelphia, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - 1835 "American Snipe" printed by R. Havell, London, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - n.d."Canada Lynx" printed by J.T. Bowen, Philadelphia, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - n.d."Carolina Parrot" printed by R. Havell, London, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - 1848"Common or Virginian Deer" printed by J.T. Bowen, Philadelphia, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - n.d."Great Footed Hawk" printed by R. Havell, London, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - 183[0?]"Great Northern Dancer or Loon" printed by R. Havell, London, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - 1844"Mink" printed by J.T. Bowen, Philadelphia, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - n.d."Purple Grackle" printed by R. Havell, London, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - 1860"Red-tailed Hawk", (elephant folio) (shelved as Poster 1860 .A84) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - 1845"Virginian Opossum" printed by J.T. Bowen, Philadelphia, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - 1828"White-headed Eagle" printed by R. Havell, London, (octavo) (Oversize OS Box T-39)
  - 1848"Yellow-bellied Marmot", (elephant folio) (shelved as Poster 1848 .A84) (Oversize OS Box T-39)